Guide to the Squatters' Collective Oral Histories Project OH 068
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series II: Interviews by Amy Starecheski, 2009-2012
  - Popeye: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, Apr 17, 2012, Jun 3, 2012 (Item OH068_Popeye_04172012_06032012)
    Popeye (Roland Llewellyn-Thomas) was raised in Toronto by a British scientist father and an American mother. He had a privileged upbringing, but was not wealthy. He came to New York City in 1975, after seeing a photo in the paper of CBGBs. He became a stripper in Times Square, and ended up experiencing the early days of punk rock, through the white downtown scene. He also experienced the early stages of hip hop, through the black and Puerto Rican scene he was involved with through hustling. He also worked as a bike messenger for fifteen years. He started squatting in the late 1980s at 327-29 8th Street, which burned down. Later he lived in a shack on the roof of Fetus, which also burned down.
  - Rick Klemann: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, Jul 13, 2012 (Item OH068_Klemann_07132012)
    Rick Klemann describes the process of getting an apartment at 544 East 13th Street, his work renovating the space, and getting water, electricity, and new windows for the building. He also talks about racialized conflicts with local teens, and the racial and gender dynamics of the squats. Klemann also discusses the legalization deal, critiques of it, and the split in his building which prevented them from moving forward.
    Rick Klemann was born in Washington, DC in 1960 and grew up in a middle class, but integrated, neighborhood. He moved to New York City in 1979 to join the art scene. In 1985 he moved into 544 East 13th Street, where he still lived as of 2012. In the late 1980s he began painting custom guitars and drums for rock bands. He most recently worked repairing generators and air conditioners.
  - Rolando Politi: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, Dec 11, 2010 (Item OH068_Politi_12112010)
    In his interview Rolando Politi discusses his role as a representative and the challenges of trying to work with the community. He also talks about the difficulties that arose as factions in the buildings began to disagree and argue. His interview contains a number of good stories about opening and working on buildings on 13th Street. Politi moved around several times because he never got very attached to a specific apartment or building. He also offers insight into the differences between European squatting and squatting in the United States.
    Rolando Politi was born and raised in Naples, Italy and was involved with social work and housing throughout Europe, especially Germany, during the 1970s and 1980s. He came to New York in 1980 and moved between different squats. In April of 1984, Politi, along with several other people, took over 539 E. 13th Street. Politi was active in the East 13th Street Homestead Coalition and served as a representative at Community Board meetings.
  - Stanley Cohen: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski and Fly Orr, Aug 15, 2012 (Item OH068_Cohen_08152012)
    In this interview, Stanley Cohen discusses his participation in legally assisting the squatter's movement. He speaks in detail about the 13th Street Adverse Possession case, for which he was the lead trial lawyer. Although Cohen and the squatters initially won the case, the ruling was overturned in the appeal process and the 13th Street squats were consequently evicted. Cohen talks about the difficulties of proving adverse possession. Cohen also discusses other legal action he was involved in, such as the conflict over fire barrels in Tompkins Square Park and defending squatters who got arrested at protests.
    Stanley Cohen is a well-known activist lawyer who started his career doing criminal defense work with Legal Aid Society in the South Bronx, and has been working on the Lower East Side since the late-1980s. He has defended many squatters arrested during evictions, and is perhaps most well-known for defending people accused of terrorism and Lynne Stewart, a lawyer found guilty of providing material support to terrorists.
  - Tauno Biltsted: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, Jan 16, 2012, Feb 15, 2012 (Item OH068_Bilsted_01162012_02152012)
    Tauno Biltsted describes the "chaotic and lovely" world of the Lower East Side in the 1980s, and how he got involved with squatting through the encampment at Tompkins Square Park. He moved into C-Squat in 1989, and describes the social and physical makeup of the building at that time, including drug use, decision-making, and the creation of the basement show space. He discusses the ABC Community Center occupation, and the complicated relationships between Tent City and the squatters, and homesteaders and squatters. He also talks about his experience living in Umbrella House. He describes the politics, organization, and physical condition of Umbrella House over the next 20 years, including rebuilding the infrastructure of the space, issues around race, record-keeping, and allocation of spaces. He discusses eviction defense, including 13th Street, and the legalization process, beginning with meetings in the early 1990s that did not lead to an agreement on legalization. Biltsted was deeply and consistently involved in the legalization process, and he discusses debates over resale value and affordability and the challenges of dealing with ownership.
    Tauno Biltsted was born in 1970 in Copenhagen, Denmark, to a Danish father and a Turkish/Canadian mother, and grew up in a hippie neighborhood in Vancouver. At age 13 his family returned to Copenhagen in search of work, and two years later they moved to East 3rd Street in New York. As a teenager he was into punk rock music and culture, and while in Copenhagen he was involved with the squatting scene there. In 1989 Biltsted moved into C-Squat in 1989 following the Tompkins Square riots. It was mostly young people, but not yet all punk rock, and included expatriate Hungarians. He was interested in taking over spaces and people running them as models for how to live in community. Biltsted later went to Europe to experience the squatting scene there in 1991-1992, and when he returned to New York he was voted into Umbrella House.
  - Thadeaus Umpster: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, Dec 14, 2010 (Item OH068_Umpster_12142010)
    In this interview Thadeaus Umpster discusses the many different squatted buildings he lived in, and his experience opening up several buildings (including in other parts of New York and other cities across the country) that lasted on average six months to two years. Umpster discusses his political involvements, especially with the organization Food Not Bombs, and the ways in which his activist work intertwined with the squatting scene. He also discusses squatting in the Bronx at Casa del Sol. Umpster also goes into detail about the difference between his perspective on squatting and that of the "old-school" squatters and squatters involved in the UHAB deal. The interview ends with a conversation about the economy, the recent recession and what it might mean for those attempting to reenergize the squatting movement.
    Thadeaus Umpster was born in Boston in 1981 and grew up on the South Shore. He remembers his first introduction to homesteading as a documentary video on homesteaders in Alaska that he saw in Junior High. In High School Umpster began listening to punk rock music which heavily influenced his political and ideological thinking. In 1999 he came to New York City to get involved in the punk and squatting scenes there.
  - Joanee Freedom: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, Aug 10, 2012 (Item OH068_Freedom_08102012)
    In this interview Joanee Freedom talks about the nineteen-year rent strike and lawsuit in her building on 6th Street and Avenue B and about her work with the garden on the corner. Freedom also tells the story of opening the squat at 544 East 13th Street and discusses gentrification in the neighborhood. She talks about Steal this Radio, the Rainbow Trading Post and Everything for Everybody, and about underground non-profit food distribution networks in the 1970s. She also discusses consensus-based decision making in these contexts. Freedom remembers the Tompkins Square Park riots and the drug scene in the neighborhood and the struggles between squatters and gardeners and drug dealers.
    Joanee Freedom is from New Jersey and came to New York City in 1980 after a period of living on communes and travelling with the Rainbow Family. She was originally involved with the Yippies and 9 Bleecker in New York City. Through her roommate, David Boyle, she got connected with the homesteading/squatting movement and was involved with the buildings on 7th Street between Avenues C and D and on 13th Street in the early to mid-1980s. After a serious car accident she was unable to participate in the physical labor of squatting.
  - Maggie Wrigley: Oral History Interview by Amy Starecheski, Jan 26, 2012, Feb 21, 2012 (Item OH068_Wrigley_01262012_02212012)
    Maggie Wrigley's interview describes the beauty and brutality of New York and the Lower East Side in the 1980s. Wrigley, who lived at Bullet Space, describes doing work days, being voted in at a meeting, and discusses how the squatter made decisions about allocating space over time. She describes the cold of those first winters, the violent atmosphere, doing work on the building, and the community of squatters and supporters. She also describes both tense and friendly relationships with their neighbors on the block. Wrigley talks about the 13th Street evictions, the defense of Umbrella House, and defending their building with barricades and petitions from the city and from non-profit housing groups. Wrigley discusses how squatters were demonized, and how they proved their good intentions by securing permanent affordable housing in the neighborhood. She also discusses her archives – why she made them, what they contain, and how she has used them. Bullet Space has historically been an artists' building, and she discusses its evolution as such, and art projects done there over the years, including Steal This Radio and Your House is Mine. Wrigley talks about how the building was run, and how it has changed with legalization. She describes the health impacts of living in a squat. Finally, Wrigley discusses the legalization process, and the challenges of dealing with UHAB and becoming homeowners, including negotiations with Margarita Lopez.
    Maggie Wrigley was born in Brisbane, Australia in 1958, and grew up in Sydney. Her father was a chemist and her mother was a teacher. After briefly attending art school she left Australia to go travelling, and stayed in San Francisco for a year, living in a punk rock warehouse and working in a punk rock club. She intended to only visit New York for a while in 1984, but felt instantly at home and decided to stay in the city where she worked in night clubs. In the winter of 1987 Wrigley started squatting at Bullet Space, after paying rent for a place in Williamsburg that had no heat or water.
  - Johanna Bartelt: Oral History by Amy Starecheski, Dec 18, 2010 (Item OH068_Bartelt_12182010)
    In this interview Johanna Bartlet talks about her experience as a squatter and discusses some of hardships of living in the cold and dusty squats. She describes what the neighborhood and the art scene were like she arrived and how it changed over time. She discusses the class and gender dynamics of the squats and in particular the macho atmosphere and conflicts between artists and housing activists. She also talks the legalization and renovation process and the shifting power dynamics in the building. In this interview Bartlet describes her art and she her more recent work teaching art to young people. She also talks about the strains and the security of life in a legalized squat.
    Johanna Bartelt grew up in a poor neighborhood in Toronto, which she was pushed out of when it gentrified. She struggled with drugs and alcohol in her twenties and moved to New York City at the age of 30 in 1985. She came to Bullet Space, a squat known for its population of artists, through Peter Missing. Bartlet remained in the squats throughout the legalization process and has taken on bookkeeping work. Bartlet is also an artist and teaches art to young students.